Register of the F. Ryan Duffy Papers, 1906-1979
Wisconsin Historical Society
F. Ryan Duffy Papers, 1906-1979
Duffy, F. Ryan, 1888-1979
Mss 679; Audio 992A; Micro 1086; PH 3659
10.4 c.f. (27 archives boxes), 1 tape recording, 3 reels of microfilm (35 mm), and photographs
Wisconsin Historical Society, Library-Archives Division
Papers of F. Ryan Duffy, a Democratic U.S. senator (1932-1938) and federal judge for the Eastern District of Wisconsin (1939-1949) and U.S. Court of Appeals for the Seventh Circuit (1949-1978), consisting of biographical material, correspondence, campaign material, legislative and judicial files, and speeches. General correspondence (1933-1973) deals with such subjects as his law firm, honors, politics, personal matters, reunions, and trips. Campaign material covers Duffy's election bids for the U.S. Senate, as well as general Wisconsin politics during the period. On Duffy's Senate career there is correspondence about various events and issues and files on patronage and legislation written or supported by Duffy. His work on copyright legislation is especially well represented.
Former Democratic senator and federal court judge Francis Ryan Duffy was born on June 23, 1888 in Fond du Lac, Wisconsin, the son of Francis F. Duffy and Hattie E. Ryan. In 1906 he graduated from Fond du Lac High School, where he was president of his class and a member of the debating, track, and baseball teams. As a student at the University of Wisconsin, Duffy was also active on the track and cross-country teams and as a member of the debating team won the William F. Vilas Medal. At the time of his graduation in 1910 he was also president of his class. One of the lasting contributions made by this class was the Sifting and winnowing academic freedom placque now on South Hall. Although the Board of Regents originally opposed the class memorial, Duffy was instrumental in its installation in 1915.
Duffy attended the University of Wisconsin law school, graduating in 1912. He then practiced law with his father in Fond du Lac in the firm Duffy Duffy. In 1917 Duffy volunteered for service in the army. Commissioned as a captain, he was stationed at Fort Brown on the Mexican border. There he was in charge of Regular Army Truck Co. # 20. Duffy then served fourteen months in France in the AEF in the Motor Transport Corps. He was discharged with the rank of major after 25 months in the service.
After the war Duffy again practiced law in partnership with his father and John P. McGalloway in Fond du Lac in the firm Duffy McGalloway. In 1922, Duffy and his father joined Russell E. Hanson in a partnership first known as Duffy Duffy and later as Duffy, Duffy, Hanson.
In 1922 Duffy also was elected commander of the Wisconsin Department of the American Legion; from 1923 through 1924 he served as national vice commander. During the years 1922-1924 he was also a member of the National Executive Committee of the American Legion.
Through his work in the American Legion, Duffy gradually became interested and involved in national politics. In 1932 he ran for the U.S. Senate and was swept into office by the Democratic landslide, defeating Republican John B. Chapple. Ideologically affiliated with the national Democratic administration Duffy was often in disagreement with the more conservative Democrats who dominated his party in Wisconsin. His position in Wisconsin became even more difficult when the liberal Progressives with whom he had much in common swept to power in the state in 1934.
In the Senate Duffy served on the Foreign Relations, Military Affairs, Appropriations, Patents, Interoceanic Canals, and Privileges and Elections committees. As a result of his work on the Patents Committee, Duffy sponsored copyright legislation which succeeded in passing the Senate, but which died in the House. Duffy was also responsible for the attempt to involve the United States in the International Copyright Union. In 1935, he was a member of the official good will party to the Far East. He also was a member of the Board of Visitors of the United States Military Academy at West Point. In 1937 Duffy was chosen as one of three World War I veterans in the Senate to dedicate American battle monuments in Europe. In this connection he made the dedicatory address at the American chapel in Flanders Field, Belgium.
Duffy ran again for the Senate in 1938, but was defeated in a three-way battle between Republican Alexander Wiley and Progressive Herman Ekern. For a short time after his defeat, Duffy resumed his law practice with Russell Hanson in Fond du Lac. In June 1939, however, President Roosevelt appointed him United States District Judge for the Eastern District of Wisconsin to succeed Judge Ferdinand A. Geiger. While judge, Duffy served on the Bankruptcy and Judicial Retirement and Tenure committees of the Judicial Conference of the United States. Ten years later after the death of Judge Evan A. Evans, President Truman appointed Duffy judge of the United States Court of Appeals for the Seventh Circuit. Between 1954 and 1959, Duffy acted as chief judge of the court. In 1966, he took on the semi-retired status of Senior Circuit Judge. Duffy retired from the court in 1978.
One of Duffy's long-term interests was the Legal Aid Society of Milwaukee. He was elected to its board of directors in 1946 and served as president in 1960. Other hobbies included golf, hunting, and fishing. Duffy married Louise Haydon of Springfield, Kentucky, in 1918. They were the parents of four children - Ann, Haydon, James, and F. Ryan Jr.
F. Ryan Duffy died on August 16, 1979 at the age of 91.
The collection consists chiefly of records from F. Ryan Duffy's senatorial and judicial careers. The material covers his life from 1906 when he graduated from high school to his death, with the majority covering the 1932-1960 period. There is little truly personal material in the collection, although his personality can be studied using his correspondence and speeches. The collection consists of biographical material, campaign material, general correspondence, speeches, and judicial and legislative files.
The collection begins with BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL and includes biographical sketches written for newspapers and Who's Who volumes, memorabilia, and an anecdotal oral history interview conducted by Milwaukee Journal reporter Richard L. Kenyon concerning Harry Truman and other famous people with whom Duffy was acquainted. Also included are numerous daybooks and diaries from the period 1935 through 1970. Although the 1939 volume is missing, two books exist for 1938 and additional extracts are available for 1935-1936 and 1951. Scrapbooks of clippings primarily from Duffy's legislative and judicial career are available on microfilm. These begin in 1906 and end in 1969. The first two scrapbooks, which cover the period 1906-1913, are more personal and cover his high school and college days. The originals of the volumes which contained photographs are available in the Visual and Sound Archives, as are the loose photographs contained in the papers. Scrapbook 4 entitled War Record, 1917-1919 consists largely of orders and military papers, although there a few letters are included. Most notable is a lengthy letter to Mrs. Duffy describing postwar conditions in France.
CAMPAIGN MATERIAL, which is arranged chronologically, consists primarily of correspondence. Included are materials on Duffy's 1932 and 1938 campaigns as well as general information on Wisconsin politics during the intervening years. Included from the 1932 campaign are itineraries for speaking engagements, bulletins and press releases, a list of Duffy workers, support and congratulatory letters, and letters to and from constituents. Material on Wisconsin politics for 1936-1938 includes statistics on the 1936 gubernatorial and presidential races, correspondence, and the Democratic platform. Information on finances of the Democratic party in Wisconsin, together with statistics and lists of contributions in the files of John J. Slocum are also included, as well as correspondence concerning the condition of the Democratic Party in 1938 and its convention. The material for Duffy's 1938 contest begins with correspondence concerning a testimonial dinner in February 1938. Also included is material on the announcement of his candidacy; endorsement resolutions from various state groups; correspondence on the management of the campaign; campaign literature; material about a potential opponent (General Ralph M. Immell) and actual opponents (Alexander Wiley and Herman Ekern); consolation letters; and correspondence and clippings concerning Samuel B. Corr, Secretary-Treasurer for Duffy's campaign, and his indictment for embezzlement in 1939. General information pertaining to both 1932 and 1938 campaigns are also included--election statistics, by county; financial statements, including an investigation in 1938 into the Duffy for Senator Club; and nomination papers (mostly 1932) and correspondence with circulators. This latter material which discusses information on Duffy's chances for victory in 1932 provides the best evidence in the collection on what Wisconsinites thought in that politically significant year.
The SENATE FILES include general and patronage correspondence and legislative files. The general correspondence, arranged alphabetically by subject, covers many topics, such as the appointment of Hugo Black to the Supreme Court in 1937 and the opposition of Duffy's constituents; Raymond J. Cannon, a Wisconsin congressman; and the Cheese War (1938) arranged by Duffy between New York and Wisconsin cheeses. Other interesting topics include the rumors of Duffy's recall in 1935 and a controversy over Elmer Serl, a farmer, and a Liberty League brochure in 1936 that gained national attention.
Correspondence concerning patronage is arranged alphabetically by name. Many names stand out for their importance to Wisconsin politics - Arthur Altmeyer, Carl R. Becker, John M. Comeford, L. Hugo Keller, Otto LaBudde, Henry Schwallbach, and John J. Slocum. Also included is a file on Patrick T. Stone, a federal judge and Duffy's brother-in-law.
The files concerning legislation introduced or supported by Duffy are arranged alphabetically by subject. The material consists of correspondence, marked copies of the legislation, and occasional research material. The largest collection of material concerns Duffy's copyright bill. Here may be found research material; correspondence with constituents, supporters, and Wallace McClure of the State Department (1935); and suggestions for changes from Mary Bendelari of the National Council of Design and others. The same type of material, though less of it, is included on the copyright treaty with which Duffy was also concerned.
The JUDICIAL FILES primarily cover the years 1939-1959, but some of the material extends to 1973. Included are reports, statistics, and legislation on bankruptcy cases (1940-1945), and material (1943-1947) on the Referees Salary Bill from the Bankruptcy Committee on which Duffy served. Files for cases for which Duffy wrote an opinion are arranged alphabetically by the title. The material in the files includes correspondence between judges, drafts of opinions, notes, court orders, and an occasional letter from a prisoner. Additional correspondence about matters that concerned Duffy as a judge or which were judicial in nature is also filed here. Examples include the Chandler Act (1939-1940), rules and appropriations for juries, and the Selective Service Act of 1940. The researcher is cautioned that there may be gaps in some of this correspondence.
Also included are form letters Duffy used as a judge, lists of his cases, and notes and instructions on his cases. The latter are divided into civil and criminal and then arranged alphabetically, with a special section under civil notes and instructions on automobile cases. Included also are statistics on Duffy's cases, such as citations used for his opinions and lists of cases appealed to the Circuit Court of Appeals and the Supreme Court.
GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE contains several categories, such as Army and Navy commissions, arranged alphabetically (which contains correspondence from people wanting Duffy to help them get commissions) and correspondence between Duffy and his law partner, Russell Hanson (1934-1941). A political file (1934-1953) is included, which contains correspondence on the Democratic Party in Wisconsin and federal elections, with Senator Joseph R. McCarthy, and with various judges around the state seeking Duffy's support for their elections. Within the reunion correspondence, for the 1950 and 1955 reunions from the University of Wisconsin, is material on the bronze plaque installed on Bascom Hall.
There is also correspondence (1938-1952) between Duffy and people seeking support from him for post-office jobs based on his past influence as a Senator, as well as letters from people serving in World War II (V Mail) and from famous people. The V.I.P. correspondence is arranged according to the status or location of the person (i.e., the White House--secretary to the President), and then by year. Duffy included lists of the letters with name, date of letter, and number received for easier reference.
SPEECHES made by Duffy form a part of this collection and cover the years 1934-1971. They are arranged chronologically and include the final draft and the notecards. Almost half of the material covers Duffy's years in the Senate, especially the years 1936-1938, when he was running for re-election. The rest of the speeches cover the period through 1971.
Administrative/Restriction Information
Presented by F. Ryan Duffy and Mrs. Louise H. Duffy, and by Don Woods, Milwaukee, 1966-1981. M66-262, M66-224, M72-164, M72-190, M72-219, M69-302, M73-375, M73-381, M73-258, M81-720
Contents List
- Biographical Material, Mss 679
  - Biographical sketches (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Daybooks and Diaries
    - 1935-1942 (Box 1, Folder 2-9)
    - 1943-1952 (Box 2, Folder 1-10)
  - Loose Papers
    - 1935-1936, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 1953-1962 (Box 3)
    - 1963-1970 (Box 4, Folder 1-8)
  - Memorabilia (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
  - Interview, 1973, Audio 992A
  - Scrapbooks (Filmed without a counter), Micro 1086
    - Volume 1, 1906-1910 (Reel 1)
    - Volume 2, 1906-1913 (Reel 1)
    - Volume 3, 1914-1924 (Reel 1)
    - Volume 4, War Record, 1917-1919 (Reel 1)
    - Volume 5, 1932 (In two parts) (Reel 1)
    - Volume 6, 1932-1938 (Reel 1)
    - Volume 7, 1933-1935 (Reel 2)
    - Volume 8, 1936-1937 (Reel 2)
    - Volume 9, 1937 (Reel 2)
    - Volume 10, 1938 (Reel 2)
    - Volume 11, 1939 (Reel 2)
    - Volume 12, 1938-1952 (Reel 2)
    - Volume 13, 1939-1946 (Reel 3)
    - Volume 14, 1953-1957 (Reel 3)
    - Volume 15, 1957-1962 (Reel 3)
    - Volume 16, 1962 (Reel 3)
    - Volume 17, 1960-1969 (Reel 3)
    - Volume 18, 1966 (Reel 3)
  - Photographs, PH 3659
    Photographs, albums, and album pages, including newspaper clippings, related to F. Ryan Duffy's years as a student at the University of Wisconsin and his political and judicial careers.
- Campaign Material, 1932-1938, Mss 679
  - 1932 Duffy campaign
    - General campaign material, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Democratic workers, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Support and congratulations, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
    - Constituent correspondence, 1932-1933 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - 1936-1938 Wisconsin politics
    - Wisconsin politics, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Democratic Party finances (Slocum file), 1937-1938 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Democratic Party, Wisconsin, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Democratic state convention, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - 1938 Duffy campaign
    - Testimonial dinner, 1938 February 7
      - Arrangements (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Ceremony (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Post-dinner (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Announcement of candidacy, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Endorsement resolutions, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Campaign material (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Opponents
      - Ralph M. Immell (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Alexander Wiley (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Herman Ekern (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Consolation letters, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Sam Corr, Embezzlement charges, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - General, 1932 and 1938
    - Election statistics (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Financial statements (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Nomination papers and correspondence (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Senate Files
  - Correspondence
    - Black, Hugo - Appointment to Supreme Court, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Cannon, Raymond J., 1936-1938 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Cheese War, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Duffy recall, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Family (Duffy) broadcast, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Judge Geiger - Impeachment, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Ralph Immell - W.P.A. appointment, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Mileage compensation, 1933-1935 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Military Affairs Committee--Panama Canal, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Press releases, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Serl Liberty League pamphlet, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Trips
      - France--Battle monuments, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Philippines, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Patronage, 1933-1938
    - A - C (Box 7, Folder 10-16)
    - D - Slocum (Box 8)
    - Patrick T. Stone (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Legislation, 1933-1938
    - General legislation, 1936-1937 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Agriculture bill, 1935 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - A.A.A. amendment, 1933 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Conservation of soil resources, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Copyright bill
      - Research material
        - Arnstein, Ira, 1931 (Box 9, Folder 6)
        - Evidence, 1931-1937 (Box 9, Folder 7)
        - Hess, Robert, 1934-1937 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence, 1934-1938
        - McClure, Wallace, 1935 (Box 9, Folder 9-10)
        - Status, 1935-1938 (Box 9, Folder 11)
        - Suggestions for change
          - 1934-1938 (Box 9, Folder 12-13)
          - Mary Bendelari, 1935 (Box 10, Folder 1)
        - Support, 1935-1937 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Hearings, 1936-1937 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Legislation
        - Senate Bill 2465, 1935 (Box 10, Folder 4)
        - Senate Bill 3047, 1935-1937 (Box 10, Folder 5)
        - Senate Bill 7, 1937 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - Notes and statements, 1935-1937 (Box 10, Folder 7)
      - Reports from lobbyists (Box 10, Folder 8)
      - Copyright Treaty
        - Research, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
        - Correspondence
          - 1934-1936 (Box 10, Folder 10-12)
          - 1937-1938 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
          - Printers and publishers, 1938 (Box 11, Folder 3)
          - Support, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
        - Legislation, 1934-1938 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Court reporters, 1937 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Daughters of the G.A.R., 1933-1934 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Exemptions from undistributed profits tax, 1937-1938 (Box 11, Folder 8-9)
    - Farm bill, 1937 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Farm loan, 1934 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Federal Trade Commission, 1935 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Food and Drug Act - Amendment, 1937 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Fur-bearing animals, 1937 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Homeowners Loan Acts, 1934-1936 (Box 11, Folder 15)
      - Reamortization of mortgages, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Indian appropriations - Amendment, 1934 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Jurors on criminal cases, Exhibitions by, 1935 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Marquette University, 1934 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Menominee Indians, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Recovery program - Amendments, 1938 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - R.O.T.C/West Point, 1935 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Revenue Act - Amendments, 1934-1936, 1934-1936 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Social Security Act - Amendment, 1937-1938 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Taxes - Property in receivership, 1935 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - U.S. postage and revenue stamps for philatelic purposes, 1935-1938 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - V.F.W. - Manitowoc Lighthouse, 1937-1938 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - War Department Civil Functions - Amendment, 1938 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Wisconsin National Life Insurance Company, 1935-1936 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - World War Adjusted Compensation Act, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Duffy bills and votes (73rd-75th Congress) (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Judicial Files
  - Bankruptcy
    - Reports, Statistics, Legislation, 1940-1945 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Committee work - Referees Salaries, 1943-1947 (Box 13, Folder 3-4)
  - Calendars - District Court, 1945-1949 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Case files
    - A - Cole (Box 13, Folder 6-8)
    - Coll - Nat'l B (Box 14)
    - Nat'l L - Un (Box 15)
    - Vi-Zi (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Arms plant condemnations, 1941-1945 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Chandler Act, 1939-1940 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Investiture
      - Pre-planning, 1937-1939 (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Induction, District Judge, 1939 (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - Congratulations, District Judge, 1939 (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - Induction, Appeals Court, 1949 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - Chief Judge congratulations, 1954 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Jury
      - General, 1939-1948 (Box 16, Folder 9-10)
      - Appropriations, 1959 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Selective Service Act of 1940, 1940-1947 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - War and defense, 1941-1945 (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Form letter book, undated (Box 16, Folder 14-15)
  - Lists of cases and notes, 1939-1949
    - 1939-1947 January (Box 17, Folder 1-4)
    - 1949 October-1949 January (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Notes and instructions
    - Civil notes and instructions
      - Book I - Automobiles (Box 18, Folder 2-3)
      - Book II-V - A-Z (Box 18, Folder 4-7)
      - Civil instructions and verdicts
        - Volume I (Box 18, Folder 8)
        - Volume II - IV (Box 19, Folder 1-4)
    - Criminal notes and instructions
      - Book I-III - A-L (Box 19, Folder 5-7)
      - Book IV-VI - M-Z (Box 20, Folder 1-3)
  - Miscellany
    - Citations for use in writing opinions, undated (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - District Court opinions, Classified by subject with a list of citations, undated (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Notes on the Lange tax case, 1946 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Cases appealed to Circuit Court of Appeals and Supreme Court, undated (Box 20, Folder 7)
- General Correspondence, 1933-1973
  - Army and Navy commissions, 1939-1944
    - A-Go (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Gr-Z (Box 21, Folder 1-2)
  - Duffy, Duffy, Hanson
    - Correspondence, 1934-1940 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Records, 1934-1941 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Honors
    - American Legion, 1943 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Honorary degrees
      - University of Wisconsin, 1952 (Box 21, Folder 6)
      - DePaul University, 1955 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - New York University, 1965 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Testimonial dinner, 1966 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Distinguished Alumnus award, 1968 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Alumnus of the year, 1969 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Miscellany (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Personal
    - F. Ryan Duffy Jr., 1938-1946 (Box 21, Folder 12)
    - Get-well correspondence, 1954 (Box 21, Folder 13)
    - Golden wedding anniversary, circa 1969 (Box 21, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous, 1933-1973 (Box 21, Folder 15-16)
    - Taylor Manufacturing Company, circa 1941-1946 (Box 21, Folder 17)
    - WMAW, 1948 (Box 21, Folder 18)
  - Political file, 1934-1953 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Post Office, 1938-1952 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Reunions
    - Fond du Lac High School - 50th, 1956 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - University of Wisconsin, 1950-1970 (Box 22, Folder 4-6)
  - Trips
    - Hawaii, 1935 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Panama Canal, 1939 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Kentucky and Washington, D.C., 1939 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Guatemala, 1950 (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - V Mail, 1943-1945 (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - V.I.P. Correspondence, 1933-1952
    - White House, 1933-1952 (Box 22, Folder 12-13)
    - Congress